Finding Aid for Samuel James Eldersveld papers, 1938-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Samuel James Eldersveld papers
1938-2010
Eldersveld, Samuel James.
851180 Aa 2
Professor of political science at the University of Michigan and Democratic mayor of Ann Arbor, Michigan for one term, 1957-1959. The collection consists primarily of Eldersveld’s mayoralty subject files. There are also some of his writings, as well as notes, course materials, correspondence, departmental memos, reports, biographical material, and recordings of interviews.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
5.5 linear feet
The collection was the gift of Samuel Eldersveld (donor no. 4992 ) and came to the library in 1970. Addition were received in 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Samuel J. Eldersveld was born March 29, 1917 in Kalamazoo, Michigan. He grew up in Muskegon, Michigan and later attended Muskegon Junior College. In 1938, Eldersveld received his B.A. from Calvin College, majoring in history. After graduation, he entered graduate school at the University of Michigan. Eldersveld received his M.A. in Political Science in 1939 with a thesis on "Quasi-Judicial Powers of Independent Regulatory Commissions." Eldersveld continued his studies at the University of Michigan, working toward a Ph.D. in Political Science. His doctoral studies were interrupted from 1942 to 1946 when Eldersveld entered the US Navy for service in WWII. Eldersveld, discharged from the Navy in 1946, returned to his studies at the University of Michigan, receiving his Ph.D. in 1946.
Eldersveld began his teaching career the same year he received his doctorate. He was hired as an instructor for the Department of Political Science at the University of Michigan. In 1947, he was promoted to Assistant Professor, followed by promotions of Associate Professor and Professor in 1952 and 1957 respectively. He later served as Chair of the Department from 1964 until 1970. In 1987, Eldersveld was granted emeritus status by the Regents of the University of Michigan.
Throughout his long, distinguished career, Eldersveld wrote 22 books and numerous articles. His major fields of study included American political parties, public opinion, elections, and comparative politics with particular focus on the Netherlands, India and China.
In 1957, Eldersveld was elected Democratic mayor of Ann Arbor, serving one two-year term.
Samuel J. Eldersveld died March 5, 2010 in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
The Samuel J. Eldersveld Papers document Eldersveld's academic career, his mayoralty, and personal background. The collection consists primarily of Eldersveld's writings, notes, course materials, correspondence, departmental memos, reports, oral history project, biographical material and mayoralty subject files. The collection contains the following series: Mayoralty Files, 1957-1959, Ann Arbor City Council, Personal/Biographical, Academic Career and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Mayors--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Municipal government--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; Eldersveld, Samuel James.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Eldersveld, Samuel James.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; University of Michigan. Dept. of Political Science.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Oral histories.; Sound recordings.
- Mayoralty Files, 1957-1959
  - Administrator (Box 1)
  - Advice letters (Box 1)
  - Aged (Box 1)
  - Airport (Box 1)
  - Annexation (Box 1)
  - Appointments, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Appointments, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Assessments (Box 1)
  - Assessor (Box 1)
  - Attorney (Box 1)
  - Biographies (Box 1)
  - Board of Supervisors (Box 1)
  - Bus, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Campaign, April 1958 (Box 1)
  - Campaign (Creal), April 1959 (Box 1)
  - Campaign (Ives), April 1959 (Box 1)
  - Campaigns (past city) (Box 1)
  - Capital improvements (Box 1)
  - Chamber of Commerce (Box 1)
  - City annual reports (Box 1)
  - City-Citizen relationships (Box 1)
  - City-Township Relations Committee (Box 1)
  - Civil defense (Box 1)
  - Clean-up (Box 1)
  - Complaints (Box 1)
  - Complaints-Party (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
  - Council procedure (Box 1)
  - County affairs (Box 1)
  - Culture-the arts (Box 1)
  - Democratic city functions (Box 1)
  - Democratic city politics (Box 1)
  - Eastbelt by-pass of US-23 (Box 1)
  - Economic Development Committee of the Chamber of Commerce (Box 1)
  - Fairview Cemetery report, March 1958 (Box 1)
  - Governmental organization (Box 1)
  - Highways (Box 1)
  - Housing (Box 1)
  - Human relations (Box 2)
  - Human Relations Commission (Box 2)
  - Industry (Box 2)
  - Jobs Committee (Box 2)
  - Market Commission (Box 2)
  - Mentally ill (Box 2)
  - Metropolitan area problems (Box 2)
  - Municipal Court (Box 2)
  - National legislation (Box 2)
  - Natural gas (Box 2)
  - Off-street parking (Box 2)
  - Parking system (Box 2)
  - Parks (Box 2)
  - Planning, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Police (Box 2)
  - Proclamations, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Proclamations, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Public works (Box 2)
  - Radio-television (Box 2)
  - Recreation, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Refuse (Box 2)
  - Republicans (city and county) (Box 2)
  - Safety, traffic (Box 3)
  - Shopping centers (Box 3)
  - Sidewalks (Box 3)
  - Southeastern Michigan Metropolitan Community Research Corporation (Box 3)
  - Speeches, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - State Legislative actions (Box 3)
  - Street paving (Box 3)
  - Taxicab Board (Box 3)
  - Taxes (Box 3)
  - Traffic (Box 3)
  - Treasurer (Box 3)
  - University-City relationships (Box 3)
  - Urban Renewal, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Water (Box 3)
  - Willow Run Redevelopment (Box 3)
  - Zoning (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous reports, memoranda, etc., 5 folders (Box 3)
- Ann Arbor City Council
  Ann Arbor City Council series contains the proceedings of the Ann Arbor City Council for the period when Eldersveld was mayor.
  - Proceedings (including background documents), April 1957-March 1959 (Box 4)
- Personal/Biographical
  Personal/Biographical series documents the life and background of Samuel J. Eldersveld. The series contains correspondence, biographical sketches, Eldersveld's curriculum vitas, and his memoirs.
  - Ann Arbor Mayor: Letters of congratulations, children's letters, 1958 (Box 5)
  - Biographical
    - Vita, etc. (Box 5)
    - "The Memoirs of Sam Eldersveld,", 1966-2010 (Box 5)
    - Essay: "An American political scientist in search of 'The secret of Soestdijk'" (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1959-2009; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Diplomas, certificates, awards, convention badges, etc. (Box 5)
  - Military service (US Naval Reserves) (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
  - Personal, 1942-2007 (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - St. Andrew's Episcopal Church, 1964; 2000 (Box 5)
- Academic Career
  Academic Career series documents Eldersveld's distinguished academic career at the University of Michigan in the Department of Political Science. The series contains Eldersveld's numerous published writings on topics such as American political parties, public opinion, elections, and comparative politics with focus on the Netherlands, India and China. Other papers in the series include research notes, writing drafts, speeches, course materials, correspondence, departmental memos, and reports.
  - Course materials; course evaluations, 1981-1997 (Box 5)
  - Dinner with the Scientific and Azazel Faculty Club to Discuss the University of Michigan Bicentennial in 2017, 1 optical disks DVD (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous and Fragmentary: contains "Speech of Mr. M.R. Masani while opening the debate on the Mid-term Appraisal of the Third Plan in the Lok Sabha on December 5, 1963" (Box 5)
  - Writings, Speeches and Reports, 15 folders
    arranged alphabetically
    - "The 1967 Indian Election: Patterns of Party Regularity and Defection,", 1969 (Box 5)
    - "American Democracy: Ideals and Reality,", circa 1990s (Box 5)
    - "A Brief History of Party Politics in Ann Arbor: One Democrat's Narrative,", circa 1990s (Box 5)
    - "Building Political Science at Michigan (1964-1971): A Brief Memoir,", circa 1970s (Box 5)
    - "The Challenge for Political Science of the Recommendations of the NSF's Special Commission on the Social Sciences,", 1969 (Box 5)
    - "The Changing American City,", 1993 (Box 5)
    - "China's 1950 Decision to Intervene in Korea: A Cost-Benefit Analysis,", 1975 (Box 5)
    - "Citizen Perceptions of Administration: A Comparative Analysis for Detroit and Delhi,", circa 1960s (Box 5)
    - "Conditions and Patterns of Political Communication,", circa 1950s (Box 5)
    - "Crisis, Instability, Continuity in the Dutch Political System: The Cruise Missiles and the 1986 Election," 1986 (Box 5)
    - "Cross-cultural Contrasts and Uniformities in Party Activism: Sweden and the United States,", 1979 (Box 5)
    - "Elite Beliefs about Democracy: Congruence and Conflict Patterns for Bureaucrats and MPS,", 1979 (Box 5)
    - "Elite Conflict Orientations in Polish and U.S. Cities,", circa 1980s (Box 5)
    - "Elite Contracts and Their Consequences: A Micro-Level Analysis of Six Nations,", circa 1970s (Box 5)
    - "Elite Ideologies and Values: System Differences,", circa 1980s (Box 5)
    - "Fulcrum of Party Power: The Urban Presidential Vote 1920-1956", 1960; 2001 (Box 5)
    - "Indian Bureaucrats--The 1964 Study," (Box 5)
    - "Indian Party Cadres and Their Supporters: 1967-1984", 1987 (Box 5)
    - "The Influence of Group Association on Political Awareness" (Box 5)
    - Misc. Notes (Box 5)
    - "Party Activists in Detroit 1956-1972; An 'Experimental' Analysis of Organizational Response to Social Change,", 1976 (Box 5)
    - "Party Activists in Detroit: A Longitudinal View 1956-1964-1972", 1976 (Box 5)
    - "The Party System and the Citizen in Kerala,", 1967 (Box 5)
    - "Poverty" Speech (Box 5)
    - "Professors in Politics,", circa 1960s (Box 5)
    - Report on the 1993 Study of Amsterdam Party Leaders, 1994 (Box 5)
    - "Some Major Results and Interpretations from the Netherlands Political Survey,", 1954 (Box 5)
    - "Some Remarks on Governmental Election Systems,", 1952 (Box 5)
    - "Some Theoretical Orientations for the Study of Parties with Opinion Surveys,", 1955 (Box 5)
    - "A Study of Political Attitudes and Affiliations in Three An Arbor Wards,", circa 1950s (Box 5)
    - "System Differences in Elite Ideologies and Values: An Exploration of Some Possible Theories,", 1985 (Box 5)
    - "System Differences in Political Elites: Patterns, Causes, Consequences,", 2000 (Box 5)
  - Published Writings, 7 folders
    - "Is the Mob So Mad?,", 1938 (Box 5)
    - "Jap Influence Fades Quickly,", 1945 (Box 5)
    - "The Influence of the Metropolitan Party Pluralities in Presidential Elections Since 1920; A Study of Twelve Key Cities,", 1949 (Box 5)
    - "British Polls and the 1950s General Election,", 1951 (Box 5)
    - "The Midwest: Confused and Quixotic,", 1952 (Box 5)
    - "Research in Political Behavior,", 1952 (Box 5)
    - "Findings and Recommendations of the Special Committee on Service Voting,", 1952 (Box 5)
    - "Democracy in Action: Political Parties,", 1952 (Box 5)
    - "The Independence Vote: Measurement, Characteristics, and Implications for Party Strategy,", 1952 (Box 5)
    - "Personal Contact or Mail Propaganda?: An Experiment in Voting Turnout and Attitude Change,", 1953 (Box 5)
    - "Experimental Propaganda Techniques and Voting Behavior,", 1956 (Box 5)
    - "American Interest Groups: A Survey of Research and Some Implications for Theory and Method,", 1958 (Box 5)
    - "The Impact of Local Party Activity upon the Electorate,", 1961 (Box 5)
    - "National Convention Leadership: 1952 and 1956", 1961 (Box 5)
    - "The Effect of Economic Conditions on Congressional Elections: 1946-1958", 1962 (Box 5)
    - "The Political Behaviour of the Indian Public and the Developing Pattern of Party Preferences,", 1964 (Box 5)
    - "Bureaucratic Contact with the Public in India,", 1965 (Box 5)
    - "Citizens and Government: A Comparative Analysis,", 1967 (Box 5)
    - "Elections and the Party System: Patterns of Party Regularity and Defection in 1967", 1970 (Box 5)
    - "Party Identification in India in Comparative Perspective,", 1973 (Box 5)
    - "Elite Perceptions of the Political Process in the Netherlands, Looked at in Comparative Perspective,", 1973 (Box 5)
    - "The American Science of Indian Politics,", 1979 (Box 6)
    - "Motivations for Party Activism: Multi-National Uniformities and Differences,", 1983 (Box 6)
    - "Elite Conflict Orientation in Polish and US Cities,", 1989 (Box 6)
    - "The American Party System: Decline and Revival?", 1992 (Box 6)
    - "The Comparative Development of Local Political Systems: An Agenda for More Research and Analysis,", 1993 (Box 6)
    - "Problem Perceptions of Chinese Local Cadres and Masses: An Empirical Study,", 1997 (Box 6)
    - "Party Change and Continuity in Amsterdam: An Empirical Study of Local Organizational Adaptation,", 1998 (Box 6)
    - "Local Elites and Popular Support for Economic Reform in China and India,", 2000 (Box 6)
    - "Support for Economic and Political Change in the China Countryside: An Empirical Study of Cadres and Villagers in Four Countries, 1990 and 1996", 2001; 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 6)
    - "Religion and Politics: How the US can again become great,", 2009 (Box 6)
  - Research, misc., circa 1950s-1990s; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Review of books, 1964-2002 (Box 6)
  - University of Michigan, Department of Political Science, circa 1960s; 1980s-1990s (Box 6)
- Sound Recordings and Videocassettes
  The Sound and Video Recordings series contains three interviews with Samuel Eldersveld regarding his personal background, academic career, and political activities. All of the interviews have been recorded on cassette tape. The 1991 interview was conducted by the APSA Oral History Program and it documents the professional and career development of Professor Eldersveld in the context of the evolution of the Department of Political Science at the University of Michigan, and within the context of the developments that have taken place within the discipline of political science during the same period. There are also three mini DVs of a 2009 interview with Eldersveld.
  - American Political Science Association, Oral History Project interview, 1991; 7 audiocassettes (Box 6)
  - Radio 16 WAAM interview with Ted Heusel, 1995 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Eldersveld regarding his career as teacher, administrator, and political activist, 1997 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Eldersveld, February 2009; 3 videotapes Mini-DV (Box 6)